Lukas Brunner

curriculum vitae



Research

I am passionate about understanding changes in global and regional climate as well as their drivers. My research includes work on the evolution of atmospheric blocking and its impacts, on the analysis of multi-model ensemble projections, and on aspects of model heritage and inter-dependence. I have published several Python packages and I am enthusiastic about all aspects of open science. My work also includes teaching, supervision, project coordination, and public outreach.

Professional Experience

01/2022 present Senior scientist, Department of Meteorology and Geophysics, University of Vienna

- Research on atmospheric blocking and temperature extremes
- Research on climate model weighting and evolution of climate models
- Work with climate data in Python and Bash using statistical learning methods
- Development and maintenance of various code repositories using Git
- Presentation of results at international conferences and in scientific journals
- Teaching, supervision of students, and public outreach

05/2018 - 12/2021

Senior scientist, Institute for Atmospheric and Climate Science, ETH Zurich

- Research on the future evolution of global and European climate
- Project coordination and cooperation with partner universities in Europe
- o Statistical analysis and visualisation of climate data with Python and Bash
- Development and maintenance of various code repositories using Git
- Presentation of results at international conferences and in scientific journals
- Teaching, supervision of students, and public outreach

10/2014 - 03/2018

Predoctoral scientist, Wegener Center, University of Graz, Austria

- Research with focus on satellite remote sensing using radio occultation
- Research on atmospheric blocking and temperature extremes
- Post-processing and statistical analysis of satellite data with Python
- Presentation of results at international conferences and in scientific journals
- Teaching, interdisciplinary cooperation, and public outreach

Research stays

04/2017 - 09/2017	Center for International Climate Research (CICERO), Norway Collaboration with Dr. J. Sillmann and publication of a scientific paper
10/2015 - 03/2016	 School of Geosciences, University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom Collaboration with Prof. G. C. Hegerl and publication of a scientific paper
06/2014	 Internships Intern, Abteilung für Luftreinhaltung, Umweltinstitut Bregenz, Austria Statistical analysis and visualization of air pollution data with R.
	Education
03/2018 Thesis	Dr. rer. nat. in Climate physics , University of Graz, Austria A new perspective on atmospheric blocking – detection, analysis, and impacts
07/2014 Thesis	MSc. in Geophysics, University of Graz, Austria Stratospheric ozone and temperature evolution over the past decades
$\frac{10/2012}{06/2008}$	BSc. in Physics, University of Graz, Austria School leaving examination
2018 - 2021	 Volunteering and Committee Work Board member (president in 2021), Club Alpbach Vorarlberg, Austria Fundraising and organisation of scholarships for the European Forum Alpbach Organisation of events, management of the Club Alpbach Vorarlberg, and collaboration with the Alpbach Foundation and other clubs
2018 - 2021	Mittelbau representative, Insitute for Atmosphere and Climate, ETH Zurich Organisation of events and contact person for internal issues
2018 - present	Reviewer for scientific journals https://publons.com/researcher/3679169/lukas-brunner/peer-review/
2016 - 2018	Volunteer, Caritas Graz, AustriaSupport of clients in an Open Learning Center
2016-2017	 Volunteer, University of Graz historical meteorological station, Austria Station upkeep and measurement of meteorological parameters
2012 - 2018	 Student representative, University of Graz, Austria Representation in several committees; Speaker of my doctoral programme
	Awards and scholarships
2018	Performance scholarship for my PhD project, University of Graz, Austria
2018	Scholarship as seminar assistant for the European Forum Alphach 2018, European

Forum Alpbach Foundation, Austria

- 2017 2018 Member PRO SCIENTIA, Österreichisches Studienförderungswerk, Austria
- 2016 2017 Scholarship for the European Forum Alpbach 2016 & 2017, Club Alpbach Vorarlberg
 - 2016 Marietta Blau Scholarship, Austrian Exchange Service
- 2009 2013 Performance scholarships (3 times), University of Graz, Austria

Invited talks

- 11/2021 **Keynote**, EC-Earth Consortium General Assembly 2021 (virtual) Uncertainties in multi-model assessments of future climate
- 10/2021 Invited talk, Wegener Center Common Space (virtual), University of Graz, Austria Weighting models by performance and independence: effects on projections of future climate

Interestes and Skills

Languages German (native), English (fluent in speaking, reading, writing)

Systems Advanced: Linux, Microsoft Windows

Coding Advanced: Python, Bash; Proficient: C++, R, SQL

Software LATEX, Git, SVN, CDO, Office applications

Hobbies Holder of the 2. Dan in Shotokan Karate; Hiking and Skiing enthusiast

Supervision and Courses

2019 - present Supervision of Bachelor and Master students

- Master's Thesis: Interannual to decadal precipitation variability in a warming climate: spatial structure and underlying mechanisms (co-supervision)
- Bachelor Thesis: Assessing climate model uncertainties an encounter with CMIP6
- Bachelor Thesis: Changes in northern hemisphere blocking occurrence under 2×CO2 based on CESM
- 2020 2021 Exercises in Systemanalyse, Bachelor course, ETH Zurich
 - Organisation of courses for over 200 students
 - Generation of exercises and preparation of the course instructors
- 2016 2018 Exercises in Methods of Modeling and Simulation with Python Master course, University of Graz, Austria (part of the course)
- 2016 2018 Exercises Introduction to Meteorology and Climate Physics Bachelor course, University of Graz, Austria (full course)
 - 2016 Seminar Selected Topics in Atmosphere and Climate Physics Master course, University of Graz, Austria (part of the course)

Published Code and Data

Dataset Liu, Y, P. Kalverla, F. Alidoost, S. Verhoeven, B. Vreede, B. Booth, E. Coppola, R. Nogherotto, **L. Brunner**, G. Harris, S. Qasmi, A. Ballinger, G. Hegerl, C. McSweeney, C. O'Reilly, T. Palmer, A. Ribes, and H. de Vries (2021): Pre-processed data of atlas in EUCP-WP2 (1.0.1). https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5679560

- Code Climate Model Weighting by Independence and Performance (ClimWIP)
 https://github.com/lukasbrunner/ClimWIP (collaborative project)
 https://docs.esmvaltool.org/en/latest/recipes/recipe_climwip.html
- Code A global blocking detection algorithm https://github.com/lukasbrunner/blocking
- Dataset **Brunner L.**, M. Hauser, R. Lorenz, and U. Beyerle (2020): The ETH Zurich CMIP6 next generation archive: technical documentation. DOI: http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3734128
- Dataset Gridded radio occultation satellite data
 - Geopotential Height: https://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11756/e4f48220
 - o Temperature: https://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11756/8245c63e
 - o Specific Humidity: https://hdl.handle.net/20.500.11756/8245c63e

Media Coverage and Public Outreach

- 11.2020 Ars Technica: Newest climate models shouldn't raise future warming projections (https://arstechnica.com/science/2020/11/newest-climate-models-shouldnt-raise-future-warming-projections)
- 02/2017 **Der Standard** (German): Atmosphärische Blockaden führen zu Kälteeinbrüchen im Frühjahr (https://www.derstandard.at/story/2000051806269/atmosphaerische-blockaden-fuehren-zu-kaelteeinbruechen-im-fruehjahr)

Publications

Peer-Reviewed

- 06/2021 Hegerl, G., A. P. Ballinger, B. Booth, L. F. Borchert, L. Brunner, M. Donat, F. Doblas-Reyes, G. Harris, J. Lowe, R. Mahmood, J. Mignot, J. Murphy, D. Swingedouw, and A. Weisheimer (2021): Toward Consistent Observational Constraints in Climate Predictions and Projections, Front. Clim., 3, DOI: https://doi.org/10.3389/fclim.2021.678109
- 11/2021 Sperna Weiland, F. C., R. D. Visser, P. Greve, B. Bisselink, **L. Brunner**, and A. H. Weerts (2021): Estimating Regionalized Hydrological Impacts of Climate Change Over Europe by Performance-Based Weighting of CORDEX Projections. *Front. Water*, 3, DOI: https://doi.org/10.3389/frwa.2021.713537
- 11/2020 **Brunner, L.**, A. G. Pendergrass, F. Lehner, A. L. Merrifield, R. Lorenz, and R. Knutti: Reduced global warming from CMIP6 projections when weighting models by performance and independence. *Earth Syst. Dynam.*, 11(4), 995–1012, DOI: https://doi.org/10.5194/esd-11-995-2020
- 09/2020 **Brunner, L.**, C. McSweeney, A. P. Ballinger, D. J. Befort, M. Benassi, B. B. B. Booth, E. Coppola, H. de Vries, G. Harris, G. C. Hegerl, R. Knutti, G. Lenderink, J. Lowe, R. Nogherotto, C. O'Reilly, S. Qasmi, A. Ribes, P. Stocchi, and S. Undorf: Comparing Methods to Constrain Future European Climate Projections Using a Consistent Framework. *J. Climate*, 33(20), 8671–8692, DOI: https://doi.org/10.1175/jcli-d-19-0953.1

- 09/2020 Merrifield, A. L., **L. Brunner**, R. Lorenz, and R. Knutti: An investigation of weighting schemes suitable for incorporating large ensembles into multi-model ensembles. *Earth Syst. Dynam.*, 11, 807-834, DOI: https://doi.org/10.5194/esd-11-807-2020
- 05/2020 Lehner, F., C. Deser, N. Maher, J. Marotzke, E. Fischer, **L. Brunner**, R. Knutti, and E. Hawkins: Partitioning climate projection uncertainty with multiple Large Ensembles and CMIP5/6. *Earth Syst. Dynam.*, 11, 491-508, DOI: https://doi.org/10.5194/esd-11-491-2020
- 09/2019 **Brunner, L.**, R. Lorenz, M. Zumwald, and R. Knutti: Quantifying uncertainty in European climate projections using combined performance-independence weighting. *Env. Res. Let.* DOI: https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab492f
- 06/2018 Unterberger, C., L. Brunner, S. Nabernegg, K. Steininger, A. K. Steiner, E. Stabentheiner, S. Monschein and H. Truhetz: Spring frost risk for regional apple production under a warmer climate. *PLoS ONE*, 13, DOI: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0200201
- 01/2018 **Brunner, L.**, N. Schaller, J. Anstey, J. Sillmann and A. K. Steiner: Dependence of present and future European temperature extremes on the location of atmospheric blocking. *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 45, DOI: https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GL077837
- 01/2017 **Brunner, L.** and A. K. Steiner: A global perspective on atmospheric blocking using GPS radio occultation one decade of observations. *Atmos. Meas. Tech.*, 10, DOI: https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-10-4727-2017
- 11/2016 **Brunner, L.**, G. C. Hegerl and A. K. Steiner: Connecting atmospheric blocking to European temperature extremes in spring, *J. Climate*, 30.2, DOI: https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-16-0518.1
- 04/2016 **Brunner, L.**, A. K. Steiner, B. Scherllin-Pirscher and M. W. Jury: Exploring atmospheric blocking with GPS radio occultation observations, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.* 16, DOI: https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-16-4593-2016

 Other publications
- 03/2020 **Brunner, L.**, M. Hauser, R. Lorenz, and U. Beyerle: The ETH Zurich CMIP6 next generation archive: technical documentation. DOI: http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3734128
- 06/2018 Mohankumar, S. E. P., K. Mintz-Woo, M. Damert, **L. Brunner** and J. Eise: Blogging Climate Change: A Case Study, In: Addressing the Challenges in Communication Climate Change Across Various Audiences. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-98294-6
- 04/2018 **Brunner, L.**: A new perspective on atmopsheric blocking from observations detection, analysis, and impacts (Dissertation). Wegener Center Verlag Graz, Scientific Report Nr. 76-2018, URL: https://wegcwww.uni-graz.at/publ/wegcreports/2018/WCV-SciRep-No76-LBrunner-Jun2018.pdf
- 06/2014 **Brunner, L.**: Stratospheric ozone and temperature evolution over the past decades (Master's thesis). Wegener Center Verlag Graz, Scientific Report Nr. 59-2014, DOI: http://wegcwww.uni-graz.at/publ/wegcreports/2014/WCV-SciRep-No59-LBrunner-Aug2014_1.pdf